Smith, Sandra mss., 2004-2015 LMC 2881
Lilly Library
Smith, Sandra mss.
2004-2015
Lilly Library
Smith, Sandra
LMC 2881
1 folio oversize
2 Boxes
The Smith, Sandra mss., 2004-2015, consist of translator's proofs, manuscripts, and clippings relating to Smith's translations from French to English.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift: 2015
Biographical Note
Sandra Smith is a Professor of French at New York University and a French-to-English translator. A member of the PEN Translation Committee and ALTA, Smith's translations include works by Irene Nemirovsky, Marceline Loridan-Ivens, Guy de Maupassant, and Albert Camus, as a biography of Jacques Schiffrin. Her translation of Nemirovsky's Suite Francaise earned her the French-American-Florence Gould Foundation Translation Prize.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printing proofs, press clippings, manuscripts, and other material related to Sandra's translations of French works into English, with an emphasis on her translations of the works of Irène Némirovsky, Albert Camus, and Guy de Maupassant. It also includes materials pertaining to Sandra's work with Irène Némirovsky's daughter Denise Epstein to promote her translation of Némirovsky's "Suite Française."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: I. Press Clippings and Book Reviews, II. Personal Correspondance (2006-2015), III. Events & Award Ceremonies (2006-2015), IV. French Theater Journals (1967-2003), and V. Printer's Proofs.
Related Materials
See PEN Translation Fund mss. and ALTA mss., also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Literature--translating; French Literature; Smith, Sandra; Camus, Albert, 1913-1960; Némirovsky, Irène, 1903-1942; Maupassant, Guy de, 1850-1893; Epstein, Denise, 1929-2013; Gille, Élisabeth, 1937-1996; Loridan-Ivens, Marceline, 1928-2018
- I. Press Clippings and Book Reviews
  - Némirovsky, Irène
    - Suite Française, 2004-2013; 3 Folders (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
    - David Golder, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Ball and Snow in Autumn, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Fire in the Blood, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - All Our Worldly Goods, 2008-2011 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Dogs and the Wolves, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jezebel, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Wine of Solitude, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - The Misunderstanding, 2012-2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Némirovsky Biographical Articles, 2006-2013 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Camus, Albert
    - The Outsider, 2011-2013 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- II. Personal Correspondance, 2006-2015 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- III. Events & Award Ceremonies, 2006-2015 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- IV. French Theater Journals, 1967-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- V. Printer's Proofs
  - The Necklace and Other Stories: Maupassant for Modern Times
    - Author's First Pass (4 folders), 2014; 4 Folders (Box 1, Folder 17-20)
    - First Pass Proof (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Second Pass Proof (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Third Pass Proof (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Final Proof (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Speaking event posters (Ovflat 32)